Guide to the Charles T. Cotton Diaries
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Charles T. Cotton Diaries
1850-1877.
Cotton, Charles T., ca. 1830-1877?
0.5 linear ft. (15 items in 1 box).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS# 0288
4079830
Biographical Note
Diarist and federal clerk in the U.S. Pension Bureau. Cotton was born in Natchez, Mississippi and taught school in nearby Pine Ridge. In 1851, he left Natchez and traveled via New Orleans and Havana to New York City and on to New Hampshire where he had relatives. By the summer of 1855 he was in St. Paul, Minnesota Territory where he clerked in a law office. At the end of 1859 he visited Natchez and Memphis, Tennessee. He moved to Washington, D.C. and in 1863 he was employed as a federal clerk in the Pension Bureau where he remained for the rest of his life. In later years he was the Recording Secretary of the Southern Republican Association.
Scope and Content
Cotton's 15 nonconsecutive manuscript pocket diaries for the period from 1850 to 1877. The diaries outline his life and travels. The entries for the Civil War years are especially interesting. He often describes the capital's fear of enemy invasion, recent nearby incursions, troop movements, and the general preoccupation with all aspects of the war. He called on President Lincoln, attended his second inauguration, and notes the passage of the Emancipation Proclamation. He describes the capital's joyous mood at the fall of Richmond and the gloom over the assassination of Lincoln. He attended the military court to see the conspirators. Later volumes talk about Pension Bureau affairs and his health and that of his family.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in one series
Series I: Diaries
Subjects
United States.--Pension Bureau.; United States.--President (1861-1865: Lincoln).--Emancipation Proclamation.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Natchez (Miss.); New Hampshire.; Saint Paul Metropolitan Area (Minn.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Washington (D.C.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.; Civil service.; Accounts.; Appointment books.; Diaries.; Financial records.; Lists.; Law clerks.; Public officers.; Teachers.
Acquisition
01/11/94 M-94-01-11 15 diaries 5285B (NYState) Purchase
- Series I: Charles T. Cotton Diaries
  - 1850 (Box 1)
  - 1851 (Box 1)
  - 1855 (Box 1)
  - 1856 (Box 1)
  - 1859 (Box 1)
  - 1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864 (Box 1)
  - 1865 (Box 1)
  - 1866 (Box 1)
  - 1871 (Box 1)
  - 1872 (Box 1)
  - 1873 (Box 1)
  - 1874 (Box 1)
  - 1876 (Box 1)
  - 1877 (Box 1)